[music]
>> Welcome to 2026 release wave two of
Business Central launch edition. This
video is something completely new
introducing
mirroring from Business Central to
Microsoft Fabric.
Now, bear in mind this is coming in
public preview in version 29.x, likely 9
29.1.
And
what is mirroring to Fabric? Well, here
on this slide you can see
the typical way we introduce Microsoft
Fabric. It's an ecosystem of data tools
such as Power BI, analytics, data
factory, and then build on a foundation
with Copilot, OneLake, and security and
governance.
And OneLake is the foundation for all
data in Fabric, and this is where you
now have the ability
to get Business Central data
synchronized live.
So, let me walk you through how to set
it up, uh how it looks the data looks in
OneLake,
the Power BI apps we ship with this, and
how you can monitor the integration if
you are an administrator.
We try to make this as simple as 1 2 3.
One, set up a mirroring database in
Fabric. Two, connect to Business
Central. Three, choose tables and
companies, click go, and that's it. And
I kid you not,
it is really that simple. Step one,
where should data be synchronized to?
You need to set up a mirroring database
in Microsoft Fabric. Here is how it
looks in the Fabric UI. You say new
database, new mirror database.
You You to give that a name.
And then it's provisioning.
And once it's done, you need to copy the
connection strings from Fabric to step
number two, which is tell Business
Central where to copy the data.
That happens in the new app for
Microsoft Fabric integration or export.
And here on the connection setup, you
need to plug in those details. Uh
where which workspace and which uh open
mirroring database you have set up in
step one.
Once you have done that, you need to go
to the Fabric menu and choose the
connect to Fabric uh action here. Now, I
did it already. The connect to Fabric
will
put our infrastructure in place, so we
are ready to copy data.
You have also a test connection action,
and there you can test if if you set it
up correctly, so that Business Central
can write data to your Fabric
environment.
Final step three, you need to specify
what data you want to have synchronized.
And that happens also in our app under
configuration. You have two choices, or
you need to specify two things. Which
tables and which companies. So, on the
table
menu here, you specify in this case, a
number of tables.
And then you need to specify which
companies. You can choose just one or
multiple companies. We'll just choose
Cronus USA here. And uh
that's was how you set it up in the UI.
You can also use configuration packages,
especially if you work with, say,
the standard Power BI apps that we ship.
We have a list of tables that that needs
to be synchronized for those apps to
work. If you have ISV solutions or other
things where that solution requires
certain tables to be synchronized, they
can specify a configuration package. You
import it here.
Um
and that sets up
uh the tables needed to synchronize.
Then, you just need one more thing.
Click start synchronization.
And that's it. As simple as 1 2 3.
Now, what How does this synchronize
data? How does it look in OneLake in
Fabric? So,
um let's dive into that Fabric platform.
This is the mirror database.
Basically, you have those tables as they
look as seen from AL are now
synchronized and created in the open
mirroring database.
And uh with Fabric, you get SQL endpoint
on these tables.
They're actually not SQL tables, they're
Delta Parquet files, but uh
that abstraction has been
like uh that has been abstracted away in
the SQL endpoint, and you can just write
SQL queries against this just as if it
was a normal SQL database.
All right. But, um we thought, let's
make sure that we we give you data in
Fabric, but we also invested a lot in
providing Microsoft providing Power BI
apps on Business Central.
Um those are sourcing data from APIs,
but we converted them as well to to work
on the Fabric backend.
In two versions, they will be available
uh soon either as code samples or on
AppSource.
Um we for each of the nine Power BI
apps, there will be a single company
version similar to the one you we ship
and the ones that are designed to be
embedded in Business Central.
But we also ship multi-company versions
so that the same Power BI app can show
data across multiple companies.
Here is an example from my Fabric
workspace where I have the mirroring
database and I have deployed two of the
multi-company
apps, one for finance, one for sales. If
I open Oh, yeah. And
if we just have a quick lineage view on
things here, you can see from this
diagram here that we have data residing
in the mirror database. We have a SQL
endpoint. We have the semantic model on
top, which is part of the Power BI, and
then the actual report.
So, how does that, let's say, finance
report look in a in a multi-company
setting?
Actually, almost the same as a single
company excepts that you now have a
filter
on where you can filter as it I want to
see data for all companies or for some
companies. And then up here, you can see
which companies you have filtered to.
And that is multi-company reporting on
Fabric with Power BI. Now, there's just
one more thing until we are done. How do
you monitor this integration if you are
an administrator?
We lock or we write two types of logs in
Business Central for for this export or
synchronization.
An overview and details.
And that data is available either in
client.
It also has APIs on it. Oh, yeah. And we
also put it in Fabric so that if you
want to monitor from Fabric point of
view, you can do that.
In client with Business Central under
the monitoring
menu, you have these two new options,
synchronization overview or details.
Here is example of the overview. We also
have supplied um
list views for all data or just if you
want to dive into the errors. And for
the details, I took that details page
just into analysis mode here
um to give you an idea of how you could
write your own mini reports. We also
have default views for
uh all data, errors, or just if you only
want to see the the synchronization
details where actually some data was
pushed over to Fabric.
Uh you can see it here.
If APIs is a thing for you instead of
using the UI, everything I showed you in
the setup and in the monitoring tables
are available as APIs.
Um the new API overview page in Business
Central, if you search for Fabric, you
can see those six APIs available there.
And if you want to monitor your Fabric
integration from from Fabric, we also
push those log files.
Uh there you can see here the export
summary, and here is uh the export
details
using the SQL endpoint in Fabric.
Finally, there is of course permissions
um part of this so that not everyone in
your organization can set up Fabric
integration. So, on the Business Central
side,
uh there are permission sets for
activation, for administrate
uh administering the the export in
general, and if you just want to read
the configuration, there's also a
permission set for that.
That's it. Just one more thing.
If you want to learn more about this,
there's a landing page called
aka.ms/bcanalytics.
If you scroll down a little bit into the
TOC, the table of content here in
Microsoft Learn, there's an article
about Microsoft Fabric and Business
Central where you can learn much more
about this new fantastic synchronization
and integration.
That's it. I hope you have a great
launch edition with lots of learning
sessions,
uh but this one is over. Have a great
day. Bye.